<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Hugo website</title>
    <link>/ABS1/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/ABS1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bayes Theorem and Conditional Probability</title>
      <link>/ABS1/2020/10/01/bayes-theorem-and-conditional-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ABS1/2020/10/01/bayes-theorem-and-conditional-probability/</guid>
      <description>Consider a medical test for a rare disease. The test quite accurate: it detects the disease with 95% probability (sensitivity of the test), and indicates the absence of the disease with 90% probability ( specificity of the test).
Notation:
 event D: person has the disease; event T: test is positive (i.e., indicates disease)  We assume that the disease has incidence of 1 %: P[D] = 0.01.
You take the test and have a positive result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exercises</title>
      <link>/ABS1/2020/08/31/the-exercise-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ABS1/2020/08/31/the-exercise-sessions/</guid>
      <description>The exercises will be held on Thursday morning for the Bioinformatics Master Students and Friday morning for the Ecology and Evolution master students. In principle, students can choose freely which session they want to addend, but this needs to be decided in the first week of the semester!
You will get an exercise series with a list of (mostly) applied problems. The teaching assistants will schedule presentations of the exercises in the first exercise session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>/ABS1/2020/08/31/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ABS1/2020/08/31/welcome/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the webpage for the course Applied Biostatistics 1. Due to current developments we are offering this course as online only. The reason for this decision is simply that this will allow us to offer high quality lectures for everyone in a unified system. A mixture of live lectures and online podcasts would be complicated to organize (we would need to limit and track the students who attend the lectures, record the lectures and exercises sessions, eventually switch the whole system in case there is a confirmed Covid19 case in our lecture, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/ABS1/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ABS1/about/</guid>
      <description>This is the webpage for the course Applied Biostatistics I.
Zoom links, course material, exercise lists and other useful material can be found on ilias.
Important: everybody must sign up on ilias for this course.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/ABS1/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ABS1/contact/</guid>
      <description>Lecturer:
Stephan Peischl stephan.peischl@bioinformatics.unibe.ch
TAs:
Maria Cuenca Maria.Cuenca@eawag.ch Johanna Ten Brink Johanna.TenBrink@eawag.ch Antoine Moinet antoine.moinet@iee.unibe.ch Rémi Matthey-Doret remi.b.md@gmail.com</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
